<!--
    Copyright 2016 DLR - German Aerospace Center
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
 -->
<documents>
	<document>
		<id>1003763</id>
		<title>Robustness and Evolvability of the Human Signaling Network</title>
		<description>
		Biological systems are known to be both robust and evolvable to internal and external perturbations, but what causes these
apparently contradictory properties? We used Boolean network modeling and attractor landscape analysis to investigate
the evolvability and robustness of the human signaling network. Our results show that the human signaling network can be
divided into an evolvable core where perturbations change the attractor landscape in state space, and a robust neighbor
where perturbations have no effect on the attractor landscape. Using chemical inhibition and overexpression of nodes, we
validated that perturbations affect the evolvable core more strongly than the robust neighbor. We also found that the
evolvable core has a distinct network structure, which is enriched in feedback loops, and features a higher degree of scalefreeness
and longer path lengths connecting the nodes. In addition, the genes with high evolvability scores are associated
with evolvability-related properties such as rapid evolvability, low species broadness, and immunity whereas the genes with
high robustness scores are associated with robustness-related properties such as slow evolvability, high species broadness,
and oncogenes. Intriguingly, US Food and Drug Administration-approved drug targets have high evolvability scores
whereas experimental drug targets have high robustness scores.
		</description>
		<publishDate>July 31, 2014</publishDate>
		<externalLink>http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003763</externalLink>
		<publisher>PLOS</publisher>
		<authors>Junil Kim, Drieke Vandamme, Jeong-Rae Kim, Amaya Garcia Munoz, Walter Kolch, Kwang-Hyun Cho</authors>
		<categoriesText>signaling networks,drug discovery,evolutionary genetics,evolutionary immunology,immune system,oncogenes,genetic networks,network analysis</categoriesText>
		<keywordsText>networks, genetic, human, signals, evolution</keywordsText>
		<license>CC-BY 4.0 http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode</license>
			</document>

</documents>
