<!--
    Copyright 2016 DLR - German Aerospace Center
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
 -->
<documents>
	<document>
		<id>1004597</id>
		<title>Distinctive Behaviors of Druggable Proteins in Cellular Networks</title>
		<description>
		The interaction environment of a protein in a cellular network is important in defining the role
that the protein plays in the system as a whole, and thus its potential suitability as a drug target.
Despite the importance of the network environment, it is neglected during target selection
for drug discovery. Here, we present the first systematic, comprehensive computational
analysis of topological, community and graphical network parameters of the human interactome
and identify discriminatory network patterns that strongly distinguish drug targets from
the interactome as a whole. Importantly, we identify striking differences in the network
behavior of targets of cancer drugs versus targets from other therapeutic areas and explore
how they may relate to successful drug combinations to overcome acquired resistance to
cancer drugs. We develop, computationally validate and provide the first public domain predictive
algorithm for identifying druggable neighborhoods based on network parameters.
We also make available full predictions for 13,345 proteins to aid target selection for drug
discovery. All target predictions are available through canSAR.icr.ac.uk. Underlying data
and tools are available at https://cansar.icr.ac.uk/cansar/publications/druggable_network_
neighbourhoods/.
		</description>
		<publishDate>December 23, 2015</publishDate>
		<externalLink>http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004597</externalLink>
		<publisher>PLOS</publisher>
		<authors>Costas Mitsopoulos, Amanda C. Schierz, Paul Workman, Bissan Al-Lazikani</authors>
		<categoriesText>drug discovery,drug interactions,protein interaction networks,drug therapy,protein interactions,forecasting,cancer drug discovery,protein structure prediction</categoriesText>
		<keywordsText>networks, protein, drug, therapy, cancer</keywordsText>
		<license>CC-BY 4.0 http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode</license>
			</document>

</documents>
