<!--
    Copyright 2016 DLR - German Aerospace Center
   
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
   
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
   
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
 -->
<documents>
	<document>
		<id>1004074</id>
		<title>Machine Learning Assisted Design of Highly Active Peptides for
			Drug Discovery</title>
		<description>
			The discovery of peptides possessing high biological activity is very
			challenging due to the enormous diversity for which only a minority
			have the desired properties. To lower cost and reduce the time to
			obtain promising peptides, machine learning approaches can greatly
			assist in the process and even partly replace expensive laboratory
			experiments by learning a predictor with existing data or with a
			smaller amount of data generation. Unfortunately, once the model is
			learned, selecting peptides having the greatest predicted bioactivity
			often requires a prohibitive amount of computational time. For this
			combinatorial problem, heuristics and stochastic optimization methods
			are not guaranteed to find adequate solutions. We focused on recent
			advances in kernel methods and machine learning to learn a predictive
			model with proven success. For this type of model, we propose an
			efficient algorithm based on graph theory, that is guaranteed to find
			the peptides for which the model predicts maximal bioactivity. We
			also present a second algorithm capable of sorting the peptides of
			maximal bioactivity. Extensive analyses demonstrate how these
			algorithms can be part of an iterative combinatorial chemistry
			procedure to speed up the discovery and the validation of peptide
			leads. Moreover, the proposed approach does not require the use of
			known ligands for the target protein since it can leverage recent
			multi-target machine learning predictors where ligands for similar
			targets can serve as initial training data. Finally, we validated the
			proposed approach in vitro with the discovery of new cationic
			antimicrobial peptides. Source code freely available at
			http://graal.ift.ulaval.ca/peptide-design/.
		</description>
		<publishDate>April 7, 2015</publishDate>
		<externalLink>http://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004074
		</externalLink>
		<publisher>PLOS</publisher>
		<authors>Sébastien Giguère, François Laviolette,Mario Marchand,Denise
			Tremblay,Sylvain Moineau,Xinxia Liang,Éric Biron,Jacques Corbeil
		</authors>
		<categoriesText>peptide synthesis,machine learning algorithms,peptide
			libraries,machine learning,drug discovery,kernel
			methods,graphs,antimicrobials</categoriesText>
		<keywordsText>peptide, learning, drug, discovery</keywordsText>
		<license>CC-BY 4.0
			http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode</license>
	</document>

</documents>
